Dr. Javier Sanz-Cruzado Puig

Personal details

E-mail: jsanzcruzado@gmail.com / javier.sanz-cruzadopuig@glasgow.ac.uk

Personal webpage: https://javiersanzcruza.github.io
GitHub profile: https://github.com/JavierSanzCruza

LinkedIn profile: https://www.linkedin.com/in/javier-sanz-cruzado-puig/

Statement

I am interested in the scientific and mathematical aspects of Computer Science, which I am presently applying in natural language processing to retrieve useful signals and information from biomedical literature. I find specific motivation in formalizing real-world problems into mathematical statements and developing principled solutions that result in effective and efficient methods when brought back to the application domain.

My current research studies the application of machine learning and natural processing techniques to evaluate the quality of biomedical research articles. The goal is to identify research articles that biomedical practitioners can annotate. Previously, I worked on the application and evaluation of recommendation techniques in the financial domain, focusing on identifying potential investment opportunities for customers. These recommendations are based on multiple data types, including customer transactions, pricing time series and knowledge graphs.

I obtained a PhD in the intersection between social networks and recommender systems, devising new people-to-people contact recommendation algorithms and considering new perspectives beyond accuracy in the development and evaluation of recommendation methods, such as the effect of link recommendation on the evolution of structural network properties and the flow of information through the network.

Professional Experience

Post-doctoral Research Associate

Since November 2021

Information Retrieval Group

IDA Section, University of Glasgow, Scotland, United Kingdom

- Text classification of biomedical literature.
- Research on recommender systems in the financial domain, portfolio optimization, knowledge graphs and profitability forecasting.
- Development of an investment recommendation platform for its use within the National Bank of Greece.
- Market analysis of the commercialization capabilities of the developed financial recommendation technologies.
- Primary investigator of two EPSRC research associate-led IAA innovation projects.
- Organization of the weekly Information Retrieval reading group.

PhD Student

June 2015 to May 2021

Information Retrieval Group (http://ir.ii.uam.es)

Universidad Autónoma de Madrid, Spain

 Research on people recommendation in social networks, social network analysis (link prediction, structural metrics, information diffusion), recommendation objectives beyond accuracy and multi-armed bandits for recommendation.

May 2019 to July 2019

Terrier Team (http://terrierteam.dcs.gla.ac.uk/)

University of Glasgow, Scotland, United Kingdom

- Research on information retrieval models for contact recommendation in social networks.
- Supervisors: Prof. Craig Macdonald and Prof. ladh Ounis.

Programmer

June 2013 to August 2013

Every View S.L., Madrid, Spain Spanish Language Route Project

- Development of the project webpage, using Joomla, MySQL and PHP, mainly web services and payment platforms.
- Development of computer game functionalities, using Unity3D and C#.

Education

PhD in Computer Science and Telecommunications

October 2016 to May 2021

Universidad Autónoma de Madrid

PhD thesis: "Contact Recommendation in Social Networks: algorithmic models, diversity and network evolution".

Score: Outstanding (Cum Laude mention)

Supervisor: Prof. Pablo Castells (pablo.castells@uam.es)

MSc in ICT Research and Innovation

September 2015 to February 2017

Universidad Autónoma de Madrid

Specialization: Computational Intelligence

GPA: 9.32/10

4 Mentions of Honor: "Information Retrieval", "Machine Learning: Theory and Applications", "Numerical and data intensive computing" and "Temporal Information Processing".

MSc Thesis: "Contact recommendation: Effects on the evolution of social networks"

MSc in Computer Science

September 2015 to February 2017

Universidad Autónoma de Madrid

GPA: 9.52/10

4 Mentions of Honor: "Advanced topics in Networking and Internet", "Embedded, distributed and ubiquitous systems", "Graphics, Multimedia and Virtual Environments", "Interactive Systems Development".

Double BSc in Computer Science and Mathematics

September 2010 to June 2015

Universidad Autónoma de Madrid

GPA: 9.23/10 (ranked in top 3% of my year)

28 Mentions of honor: including "Artificial Intelligence", "Neurocomputing", "Information Search and Mining" and "Fundamentals of Machine Learning".

BSc Thesis: "Metasearch engine with session management and interleaving A/B testing".

An updated list of publications can be accessed from https://javiersanzcruza.github.io/pubs.

- Guo, L., Sanz-Cruzado, J., McCreadie, R. University of Glasgow at the FinLLM Challenge Task: Adapting Llama for Financial News Abstractive Summarization. Joint Workshop of the 8th Financial Technology and Natural Language Processing (FinNLP) and the 1st Agent AI for Scenario Planning (AgentScen) at the 33rd International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI 2024). Jeju, Republic of Korea, August 2024, pp. 127-132. https://aclanthology.org/2024.finnlp-2.12/
- Kim, Y., Lee, Y., Sanz-Cruzado, J., McCreadie, R., Lee, Y. Stock Recommendations for Individual Investors: A Temporal Graph Network Approach with Mean-variance Efficient Learning. *IJCAI 2024 Workshop on Recommender Systems in Finance (Fin-RecSys) at the 33rd International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI 2024)*. Jeju, Republic of Korea, August 2024
- Guo, L., Sanz-Cruzado, J., McCreadie, R. Comparing the Impact of Financial Knowledge Graphs from Financial Reports and Wikidata in Asset Recommendation. *IJCAI 2024 Workshop on Recommender Systems in Finance (Fin-RecSys), at the 33rd International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI 2024)*. Jeju, Republic of Korea, August 2024.
- Sanz-Cruzado, J., Droukas, N., McCreadie, R. FAR-Trans: An Investment Dataset for Financial Asset Recommendation. *IJCAI 2024 Workshop on Recommender Systems in Finance (Fin-RecSys), at the 33rd International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI 2024)*. Jeju, Republic of Korea, August 2024. https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08692
- Sanz-Cruzado, J., Richards, E., McCreadie, R. FAR-AI: A Modular Platform for Investment Recommendation in the Financial Domain. *46th European Conference on Information Retrieval (ECIR 2024)*. Demo track. Glasgow, United Kingdom, March 2024, Vol. V, pp. 267-271. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-56069-9 30
- Sanz-Cruzado, J., McCreadie, R., Droukas, N., Macdonald, C., Ounis, I. On Transaction-Based Metrics as a Proxy for Profitability of Financial Asset Recommendation. 3rd International Workshop on Personalization and Recommender Systems in Financial Services (FinRec 2022) at the 16th ACM Conference on Recommender Systems (RecSys 2022). Seattle, Washington, USA, September 2022.
- Sanz-Cruzado, J. Castells, P. RELISON: A Framework for Link Recommendation in Social Networks.
 45th International ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR 2022). Resource track. Madrid, Spain, July 2022, pp. 2992-3002.
 https://doi.org/10.1145/3477495.3531730
- Sanz-Cruzado, J., Castells, P., Macdonald, C., Ounis, I. Effective contact recommendation in social networks by adaptation of information retrieval models. *Information Processing & Management* 57(5), September 2020, Article 102285. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ipm.2020.102285
- Sanz-Cruzado, J., Macdonald, C. Ounis, I., Castells, P. Axiomatic Analysis of Contact Recommendation Methods in Social Networks: an IR Perspective. 42nd European Conference on Information Retrieval (ECIR 2020). Online, April 2020, pp. 175-190. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-45439-5
- Sanz-Cruzado, J., Castells, P., López, E. A simple multi-armed nearest-neighbor bandit for interactive recommendation. 13th ACM Conference on Recommender Systems (RecSys 2019). Copenhaguen, Denmark, September 2019, pp. 358-362. https://doi.org/10.1145/3298689.3347040
- Sanz-Cruzado, J., Castells, P. Beyond Accuracy in Link Prediction. 3rd Workshop on Social Media for Personalization and Search (SoMePeAs 2019) at the 41st European Conference on Information Retrieval (ECIR 2019). Cologne, Germany, April 2019. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-52485-2

 Sanz-Cruzado, J., Castells, P. Information Retrieval Models for Contact Recommendation in Social Networks. 41st European Conf. on Information Retrieval (ECIR 2019). Cologne, Germany, April 2019, pp. 148-163.

https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-15712-8 10

- Sanz-Cruzado, J., Castells, P. Contact Recommendations in Social Networks. In: S. Berkovsky, I. Cantador, D. Tikk (Eds.): *Collaborative Recommendations: Algorithms, Practical Challenges and Applications*. World Scientific Publishing, November 2018. ISBN: 978-981-3275-35-5, pp. 519-570. https://doi.org/10.1142/9789813275355_0016
- Sanz-Cruzado, J., Castells, P. Enhancing Structural Diversity in Social Networks by Recommending Weak Ties. 12th ACM Conference on Recommender Systems (RecSys 2018). Vancouver, Canada, October 2018, pp. 233-240.

https://doi.org/10.1145/3240323.3240371

- Sanz-Cruzado, J., Pepa, S.M., Castells, P. Recommending Contacts in Social Networks Using Information Retrieval Models. 5th Spanish Conference on Information Retrieval (CERI 2018). Zaragoza, Spain, June 2018, pp. 19:1-19:8.
 - https://doi.org/10.1145/3230599.3230619
- Sanz-Cruzado, J., Pepa, S.M., Castells, P. Structural Novelty and Diversity in Link Prediction. 9th International Workshop on Modelling Social Media (MSM 2018) at The Web Conference (WWW 2018). Lyon, France, April 2018.

https://doi.org/10.1145/3184558.3191576

Teaching

Web search and data mining labs, 4th year BSc Computer Science

January to May 2018, 2019, 2020

Analysis of algorithms labs, 2nd year BSc Computer Science

September 2019 – January 2020

Guest lecture on evaluation and production of recommender systems at the recommender systems course at the IE University (in Spanish)

April 2022

BSC thesis supervision (co-supervised with Prof. Pablo Castells, Universidad Autónoma de Madrid)

- Miranda, B. "Information Diffusion Modeling on Twitter"
 2017-2018
- Amor, A. "Link prediction and recommendation in social networks"
 2018-2019
- o López, E. "Multi-armed Bandits in Recommendation" 2018-2019

Level 4 BSc thesis supervision (co-supervised with Dr. Richard McCreadie, University of Glasgow)

- Lunny, L. "iTrade: The financial portfolio generation tool"
 2022-2023
- o Mousa, J. "TradeMind" 2022-2023

Assistance on PhD supervision (main supervisor: Dr. Richard McCreadie, University of Glasgow)

- Guo, L.: Automated knowledge graph construction for financial time series forecasting and summarization

 2022-Now
- Richards, E.: Explainable question answering systems with the assistance of large language models
 2022-Now

Grants, scholarships and awards

PhD scholarship (FPU Grant), Spanish Government.

September 2018 – May 2021

PhD scholarship (FPI Grant), Universidad Autónoma de Madrid.

March 2017 – September 2018

Research scholarship in MSc studies, Universidad Autónoma de Madrid.

October 2015 – October 2016

Excellence scholarship in BSc Studies, Regional Government of Madrid. 2012 – 2015 (every year)

Research interests

Social Networks: analysis, link prediction, information diffusion.

Information Retrieval: recommender systems, evaluation, novelty, and diversity.

Reinforcement learning: multi-armed bandits.

Financial technologies: profitability forecasting, robo-advisors, portfolio optimization

Technical skills

Programming languages: Java, Python, C, PHP, MatLab.

Databases: MySQL, PostgreSQL, QuestDB.

Operating systems: Microsoft Windows (XP, Vista, 7, 8, 10), Unix (Ubuntu, CentOS).

Other tools: Maven, Git, Docker, Kubernetes (OpenShift).

General purpose software: LaTeX, Microsoft Office (Word, Excel & PowerPoint).

Participation in Research projects

Creation of a knowledgebase of high quality assertions of the clinical actionability of somatic variants in cancer August 2024– Present

Reference number: 1U24CA275783-01

Automated information extraction from clinical research for the creation of a cancer knowledge

base.

Institution: University of Glasgow

Funding body: National Institutes of Health (USA)

PI: Jake Lever

Role: post-doctoral researcher

ICURe Explore programme

October 2023 – January 2024

Market analysis of the commercialization potential of a developed financial asset recommendation platform in previous projects (FAR-AI, PPC-FI and Infinitech).

Institution: University of Glasgow Funding body: Innovate UK Role: entrepreneurial lead

FAR-AI: Deployment of AI-Based Financial Asset Recommendation System

Reference number: EP/X525716/1

August 2023 – October 2023

Data collection of London Stock Exchange companies, and integration of the data on a financial asset recommendation and portfolio management platform for the UK market.

Institution: University of Glasgow

Funding body: UKRI EPSRC Impact Acceleration Account

PI: Javier Sanz-Cruzado Role: primary investigator

PPC-FI: Personalized portfolio construction for financial investments April 2023 – July 2023

Reference number: EP/X525716/1

Development of automated portfolio construction and management algorithms and their integration within a financial recommendation platform for the Greek market.

Institution: University of Glasgow *Partners:* National Bank of Greece

Funding body: UKRI EPSRC Impact Acceleration Account

PI: Javier Sanz-Cruzado Role: primary investigator

Infinitech November 2021 – March 2023

Reference number: 856632

Research on recommendation technologies for the financial domain, and development of an

investment recommendation platform for the Greek market.

Institution: University of Glasgow *Partners:* National Bank of Greece

Funding body: European Comission Horizon 2020 PI: ladh Ounis, Craig Macdonald, Richard McCreadie

Role: post-doctoral research associate

Beyond static recommendation: equity, interaction and transparency June 2020 – May 2021

Reference number: PID2019- 108965GB-I00

Research on people recommendation algorithms in online social networks.

Institution: Universidad Autónoma de Madrid

Funding body: Spanish government

PI: Pablo Castells Azpilicueta, Iván Cantador

Role: pre-doctoral researcher

Recommendation in social media: context, diversity and algorithmic bias

Reference number: TIN2016-80630-P December 2016 – December 2019

 $Research\ on\ people\ recommendation\ algorithms\ in\ online\ social\ networks\ and\ multi-armed\ band it$

algorithms for recommendation.

Institution: Universidad Autónoma de Madrid

Funding body: Spanish government

PI: Pablo Castells Azpilicueta, Iván Cantador

Role: pre-doctoral researcher

Voxpopuli: efficient analysis of reputation, propagation, and recommendation in social media environments June 2014 – December 2016

Reference number: TIN2013-47090-C3-2-P

Research on people recommendation algorithms in online social networks.

Institution: Universidad Autónoma de Madrid

Funding body: Spanish government

PI: Pablo Castells Azpilicueta
Role: pre-doctoral researcher

Languages

Spanish: Native Speaker.

English: Working proficiency.

• Certificate of Advanced English – Cambridge University

July 2018

Level 2 Certificate in ESOL International.

Common European Framework of Reference (CEFR) C1 Level.

• **Graded Examination in Spoken English, Grade 11** – Trinity College London

Level 2 Certificate in ESOL International (Speaking and Listening). CEFR C1.2 level.

French: Basic notions.

Other activities

Students' representation:

 PhD students' representative in Computer Science department 	2017 to 2021
BSc students' general delegate	2014 to 2015
 Students' representative in "New Curricula" commission 	2014 to 2015
Course delegate	2011 to 2016

Software development and maintenance

RELISON framework: Java social network analysis and recommender Systems framework (https://iruam.github.io/RELISON/).

RankSys framework: Java recommender Systems framework (http://ranksys.org).

Hackathons:

• Infinitech Hackathon 16th-17th June 2022

Team Infinithree – with Edward Richards and Lubingzhi Guo

Position: 1st

Developed profitability prediction algorithm with knowledge graph embeddings.

Infinitech Hack Challenge
 Team Infinithree – with Maanasa Shrikrishna and Edward Richards

24th November 2021

Position: 1st

Developed profitability prediction algorithm with sentiment analysis extracted from news.

Invited talks:

- **Invited talk** at the University of Glasgow IR seminars, titled "Investors are (not) always right: A comparison of transaction-based and profitability-based evaluation in financial asset recommendation" (*June 2024*).
- Invited talk at the University of Glasgow IR seminars, titled "On Transaction-Based Metrics as a Proxy for Profitability of Financial Asset Recommendations" (October 2022).
- **Invited talk** at the University of Glasgow IR seminars, titled "Recommending people in social networks: algorithmic models and network diversity" (*February 2022*).
- **Invited talk** at the HaiVis group at the Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile, titled "Contact recommendation in social networks using search methods" (in Spanish, *March 2021*).
- **Invited talk** at the Universidad Española de Educación a Distancia, titled "Contact recommendation in social networks: beyond accuracy" (in Spanish, *July 2018*).

Reviewer

- Reviewer of ACM Transactions on Information Systems journal (ACM TOIS).
- Reviewer of the User Modeling and User-Adapted Interaction journal (UMUAI).
- Reviewer of the ACM Transactions on the Web journal (ACM TWEB).
- Reviewer of the AI Communications journal.
- Reviewer of the Artificial Intelligence and Law journal
- Program committee member for the 5th ACM Conference on AI in Finance (ICAIF 2024)
- Short paper program committee member for the 47th ACM Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR 2024).
- Program committee member for the 46th Conference on Information Retrieval (ECIR 2024).
- Program committee member for the 16th ACM Conference on Recommender Systems (RecSys 2022).
- Program committee member for the 44th Conference on Information Retrieval (ECIR 2022).

- **Program committee member** for the 45th ACM Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR 2022).
- Program committee member for the 15th ACM Conference on Recommender Systems (RecSys 2021).
- Short paper program committee member for the 44th International ACM *SIGIR* Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR 2021).
- Subreviewer for The Web Conference 2021 (TheWebConf 2021).
- **Reviewer** for the latest-breaking results track for the 14th ACM Conference on Recommender Systems (RecSys 2020).

Organization

- Local committee member / volunteer at the 46th Conference on Information Retrieval (ECIR 2024).
- Organizer of a workshop titled "What's my next investment? Automated recommendations for investors?" at the University of Glasgow, as part of the Scottish Fintech Festival (October 2023).
- Organizer of the IR reading group at the University of Glasgow (October 2022 now).
- Student volunteer at the 13th ACM Conference on Recommender Systems (RecSys 2019).

References

Prof. Pablo Castells

Universidad Autónoma de Madrid & Amazon

Phone: (+34) 91 497 2106 E-mail: pablo.castells@uam.es

Prof. ladh Ounis

University of Glasgow

E-mail: <u>iadh.ounis@glasgow.ac.uk</u>

Prof. Craig Macdonald

University of Glasgow

E-mail: craig.macdonald@glasgow.ac.uk

Dr. Richard McCreadie

University of Glasgow

E-mail: richard.mccreadie@glasgow.ac.uk

Dr. Jake Lever

University of Glasgow

E-mail: jake.lever@glasgow.ac.uk